<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Act of Contrition in Lushootseed</title>
          <author> Dawn Bates and Deryle Lonsdale </author>
          <respStmt><resp> Text Encoding by </resp><name>Deryle Lonsdale</name></respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><publisher>Deryle Lonsdale</publisher><address><addrLine>4039 JFSB, Provo, UT 84097</addrLine></address><availability status="unknown"><p>This information may not be reproduced without the explicit permission from the copyright holder. For copyright information, please contact Deryle Lonsdale at lonz@byu.edu</p></availability></publicationStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="true">There are two versions of the Lord's Prayer in Romanized Lushootseed.</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc><p>Source description</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
          <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
      </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
      <front>
          <div>
              <listWit>
                      <witness xml:id="Ch">Chirouse</witness>
                      <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
                      <witness xml:id="LB">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
                      <witness xml:id="CBL">Chirouse -- Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
              </listWit>
          </div>
      </front>
      
      <body>
          <l n="1">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch">Confiteor.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">THE CONFITEOR.</rdg>                  
                  <rdg wit="#LB">THE CONFITEOR.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL">Gloria Patri: the Confiteor</rdg>
             </app></l>
            
          <l n="2">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> 콅rh캐rh캒 -sbil캐l캒mch캣d twal de Sherhk Siam, lilzir kw캡kr twal ki mok stam, </rdg> 
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">Rarasmilalamched dhual di Sherk-Siam lilhzihu kwerkru dhual kwi boku stab,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">x팳팳ax팳asbil'툾alla툾톛b c팳톛d dx퉝툾al di s팳톛q si툾ab li톫퉋ix퉝 q퉝iq퉢퉝 dx퉝툾al  k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 stab,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> 툾ux팳팳ax팳asbil'툾alla툾톛b c팳톛d dx퉝툾al di s팳톛q si툾ab li톫퉋ix퉝 q퉝iq퉢퉝 dx퉝툾al  k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 stab, </rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="3">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> twalde telh alh Maly skw캐kh캡d durhkalap,</rdg> 
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual tsde telh halh Mari tskwakred duhkralap,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">dx퉝툾al di t톛톫 ha툾톫 Mari ck퉢퉝aqid dx퉝qal톛p,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> dx퉝툾al di t톛톫 ha툾톫 Mari ck퉢퉝aqid dx퉝qal톛p,</rdg>
              </app></l>
            
          <l n="4">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> twald캡 St. Michel alcange, twal d캣 St. Jean Baptiste, twalde les Ap콄tres St. Piere 캡 St. Paul (gwal Sherk Siam Tjussand) </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual di Sen-Mishel Akash, dhual di Sen-San-Batis, dhunal di Sen-Piel eba Sen-Pol, gwalh Sherk-Siam schiss^ad,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">dx퉝툾al di Sen-Mishel Akash, dx퉝툾al di Sen-San-Batis, dx퉝툾al di Sen-Piel 툾ib톛 Sen-Pol, g퉝톛톫 s팳톛q si툾ab sc팳톛sad,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> dx퉝툾al di S톛n-Mich톛l Akash, dx퉝툾al di S톛n-San-Batis, dx퉝툾al di S톛n-Pi톛l 툾i ??? S톛n-Pol, g퉝톛톫 s팳톛q si툾ab sc팳톛sad,  </rdg>
              </app></l>

          <l n="5">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> ema twal mok tol sherk ass킗lhtam캡rh, klal bass캶sta, twal degwe dsgwa deban (Leplet.)  </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">eba dhual boku gwalh sherk satsilhtalbihu 'tlalba asista dhual dgwe dsgwa deban,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">툾ib톛 dx퉝툾al b톛k퉢퉝 g퉝톛톫 s팳톛q s툾aci톫talbix퉝 쿹al퉢b톛as툾ist톛툾 dx퉝툾al d톛g퉝i dsg퉝a툾 dbad,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> 툾i ??? dx퉝툾al b톛k퉢퉝 tul' s팳톛q 툾aci톫talbix퉝, 쿹al퉢b톛as툾ist톛툾, dx퉝툾al d톛g퉝i dsg퉝a툾 dbad, </rdg>
              </app></l>
   
          <l n="6">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> T캡캡lh kh캐 tudskwadched atechispetedgwassem, </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual tih^ilh kra tu tskwadad ate disduhspet^edegwasseb,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">dx퉝툾al ti툾i톫 x퉝a툾 tu퉋톛k퉢퉝adad 툾톛 t톛 dsdx퉝sp톛tidg퉝as톛b,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> ti툾i톫 qa tu퉋톛k퉢퉝ad c팳톛d 툾톛 dis팳톛툾 sp톛tidg퉝as톛b, </rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="7">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> At캡deschgw캐dgw캒d, atedech s킗ayus, atedesch w캡ladsi캐yus, </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">ate disduhsgwadgwad, ate disduhsiayus eba te wheladisduhsiayus,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">툾톛 t톛 dsdx퉝sg퉝adg퉝ad, 툾톛 t톛 dsdx퉝syayus 툾ib톛 t톛 x퉝i툾l톛dx퉝syayus,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> 툾톛 t톛 dx퉝sg퉝adg퉝ad, 툾톛 t톛 dx퉝syayus,  툾톛 t톛 dx퉝sw톛ladsyayus, </rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="8">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> atedsgw캐 skhop derhach (bis). 캒tedsgw캐 ik 캒skh콆p dr캒ch </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">ate dsgwa askrop drech, ate disgwa askrop drech, ate dsgwa heku askrop drech.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">툾톛 t톛 dsg퉝a툾 툾톛sq톛p dx팳톛c팳, 툾톛 t톛 dsg퉝a툾 툾톛sq톛p dx퉝팳톛c,  툾톛 t톛 dsg퉝a툾 hik퉝 툾톛sq톛p dx퉝팳톛c팳.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> 툾톛 t톛 dsg퉝a툾 sq톛p dx팳톛c팳, 툾톛 t톛 dsg퉝a툾 sq톛p dx팳톛c팳,  툾톛 t톛 dsg퉝a툾 hik퉝 툾톛sq톛p dx팳톛c팳. </rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="9">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> Delh sorhot캡캡ch twal ts캡캡lh alh Maly skwakhed duk캐l캒p, </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">Dilh tsahu otehech dhual tsde telh halh Mari tskwakred duhkralap,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">di톫 c톛x퉝 툾utihic팳 dx퉝툾al tsi di t톛톫 ha툾톫 Mari ck퉢퉝aqid dx퉝qal톛p,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> di톫 s톛x퉝ut'iwi톫 dx퉝툾al tsi툾i톫  ha툾톫  Mali ck퉢퉝aqid dx퉝qal톛p,</rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="10">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> Twal ta St. Mishel alcange, twal ta St. Jean Baptiste,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual di Sen-Mishel Akash, dhual di Sen-San-Batis,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">dx퉝툾al di Sen-Mishel Akash, dx퉝툾al di Sen-San-Batis,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> dx퉝툾al t톛 S톛n-Mich톛l alkash, dx퉝툾al t톛 S톛n-San-Batis ,</rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="11">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> twalta St. Pierre ema St. Paul gwalh Sherk Siam chussand</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual di Sen-Piel eba Sen-Pol gwalh Sherk-Siam schiss^ad </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">dx퉝툾al di Sen-Piel 툾ib톛 Sen-Pol, g퉝톛톫 s팳톛q si툾ab sc팳톛sad</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> dx퉝툾al t톛 S톛n-Pi톛l 툾i ??? S톛n-Pol , g퉝톛톫  s팳톛q si툾ab sc팳톛sad</rdg>
              </app></l>

          <l n="12">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> twal mok gwalh Sherhk 캐ss킗lht캒m캡rh </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">eba dhual boku gwalh sherk satsilhtalbihu</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">툾ib톛 dx퉝툾al b톛k퉢퉝 g퉝톛톫 s팳톛q s툾aci톫talbix퉝</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> dx퉝툾al b톛k퉢퉝 g퉝톛톫 s팳톛q s툾aci톫talbix퉝  </rdg>
              </app></l>

          <l n="13">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch">  ema twalh d캣gw캐  d캣b캐n (l캣pl캡t) ,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">'tlalba asista dualh dgwe dsgwa deban,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB"> 쿹'a톫'b톛툾톛s툾ist톛툾 dx퉝툾al d톛g퉝i dsg퉝a툾 d톛bad.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL">툾i ??? dx퉝툾al d톛g퉝i d톛bad. </rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="14">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch">chalap tlha t캡캡chtomsh tw캒l d캡  Sherkh-Siam sgwachelh s캡rhs킗캐mchelh (twal tsa)</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo">chalap tlo tehechtobsh dhual di Sherk-Siam sgwachelh sihusiamchelh dhual tsa.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB">c팳톛l톛p 톫utihic팳tubs팳 dx퉝툾al di s팳톛q si툾ab sg퉝a툾c팳톛톫 six퉝si툾abc팳톛톫 dx퉝툾al 툾톛ca.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL">c팳톛l톛p 톫ut'iwi톫tubs팳 dx퉝툾al di  s팳톛q si툾ab sg퉝a툾c팳톛톫 six퉝si툾abc팳톛톫 dx퉝툾al 툾톛ca.</rdg>
              </app></l>
          
          <l n="15">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#Ch"> Klob assista</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Bo"> 'Tlob asista</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#LB"> 쿹'ub 툾톛s툾ist톛툾.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#CBL"> 쿹'ub 툾톛s툾ist톛툾.</rdg>
              </app></l>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>