<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit cat칠chisme des indiens", 4e le칞on -->
    
    <body>
      <p>LESSON V.</p>
            
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Tu e'tl o kwi Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam dhual swatihuhted, gula tu hoyutsut atsilhtalbihu? </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. tu툾톛쿹퉢 툾u k퉝i b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab dx퉝툾al swatix퉝t톛d, g퉝톛l tuhuyutcut 툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LWG">1. went Q the son of the sky nobleman unto earth then made+self man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. Did the Son of God go to earth and make himself a man?</rdg>
        </app></l>

      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, tu e'tl kwi Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam dhual ku swatihuhted gula tu hoyutsut atsilhtalbihu.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, tu툾톛쿹퉢 k퉝i b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab dx퉝툾al k퉝i swatix퉝t톛d g퉝톛l tuhuyutcut 툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes went the son of the sky nobleman unto earth then made+self man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, the Son of God did go to earth and make himself a man.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Tu kudatob o a kwi Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam ku dcho tsokwab rolab aku tsokwabchelh eku dcho sele rolab aku selechelh.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. tuk퉝톛dat톛b 툾u 툾톛 k퉝i b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab k퉝i d톛c팳'u툾 c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b x팳퉝ul퉢ab 툾톛 k퉝i c퉢uk퉢퉝톛bc팳톛톫 툾i k퉝i d톛c팳'u툾 sh톛li? x팳퉝ul퉢ab 툾톛 k퉝i sh톛li툾c팳톛톫.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">2. taken Q by the son of the sky nobleman the one body like of the body+our and the one soul like of the soul+our</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. Did the Son of God take a body like our body and a soul like our soul?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, tu kudatob a kwi Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam ku dcho tsokwab rolab aku tsokwabchelh eku dcho sele rolab aku selechelh;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, tuk퉝톛dat톛b 툾톛 k퉝i b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab k퉝i d톛c팳'u툾 c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b x팳퉝ul퉢ab 툾톛 k퉝i c퉢uk퉢퉝톛bc팳톛톫 툾i k퉝i d톛c팳'u툾 sh톛li툾 x팳퉝ul퉢ab 툾톛 k퉝i sh톛li툾c팳톛톫</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes taken by the son of the sky nobleman the one body like of the body+our and the one soul like of the soul+our</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, the Son of God took a body like our body and a soul like our soul.</rdg>
        </app></l>          
       
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">asista ku tu dahu hoyils atsilhtalbihu.  </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾톛s툾ist톛툾 k퉝i tud톛x퉝huyils 툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">this the way-made human</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">This is how He became man.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Al o ku 'tlach akus halh duhkralap Mari ku tus hois atsilhtalbihu Beda, a kwi Sherk-Siam?  </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">3. 툾al 툾u k퉝i 쿹퉢ac팳 툾톛 k퉝si ha툾톫 dx퉝qalap Mali k퉝i tushuys 툾aci톫talbix퉝 b톛da툾, 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">3. in Q the belly of the good virgin Mary the making man son of the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">3. Was it in the womb of the blessed virgin Mary that the Son of God was made man?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, al ku 'tlach akus halh duhkralap Mari ku tus hois atsilhtalbihu Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL"> 툾i, 툾al k퉝i 쿹퉢ac팳 툾톛 k퉝si ha툾톫 dx퉝qalap Mali k퉝i tushuys 툾aci톫talbix퉝 b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes in the belly of the good virgin Mary the making man son of the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, it was in the womb of the blessed virgin Mary that the Son of God was made man.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                        
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">4. Whe o ku tus willes kwi dokwibalh Beda adokwibalh a aku tus hois atsilhtalbihu?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">4. x퉝i툾 툾u k퉝i tusx팳퉝il퉢i(l)s k퉝i duk퉝ib톛톫 b톛da툾 툾톛 duk퉝ib톛톫 툾a 툾톛 k퉝i tushuys 툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">4. not Q the lose the Changer son  Changer there of the made man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Didn't the Son of God lose God when He became man?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                            
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe ku tus willes kwi dokwibalh Beda a dokwibalh a aku tus hois atsilhtalbihu; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">x퉝i툾 k퉝i tusx팳퉝il퉢i(l)s k퉝i duk퉝ib톛톫 b톛da툾톛 duk퉝ib톛톫 툾a 툾톛 k퉝i tushuys 툾aci톫talbix퉝 ; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">not the lose the changer son of changer there of the made man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">No, the Son of God did not lose God when He became man.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">tskwakred dokwibalh tsid칥lh tor ba atsilhtalbihu. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ck퉢퉝aqid duk퉝ib톛톫 c톛di톫 tux팳퉝 b톛툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">always changer that although man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">He is always God even though man.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                    
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">5. Gwat kwi tu sda a kwi Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam aku tus hois atsilhtalbihu?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">5. g퉝wat k퉝i tusda툾 툾톛 k퉝i b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab 툾톛 k퉝i tushuys 툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">5. what the past  name of the son of the sky nobleman at+the past made man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">5. What was the name of the Son of God when he was made man?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                        
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Shesu-Kri ku tu sda a kwi Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam aku tus hois atsilhtalbihu.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">Shesu-Kri k퉝i tusda툾 툾톛 k퉝i b톛da 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab 툾톛 k퉝i tushuys 툾aci톫talbix퉝.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">Jesus Christ the past  name of the son of the sky nobleman at+the past made man</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Jesus Christ was the name of the Son of God when he was made man?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                            
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">6. Dhual asared ku tus hoyutsuts atsilhtalbihu Beda akwi Sherk-Siam? </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">6. dx퉝툾al 툾톛s툾톛x팳id k퉝i tushuyucuts 툾aci톫talbix퉝 b톛da툾 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">6. unto why the past made+self man son of+the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Why did the Son of God make himself a man?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tu hoyutsut atsilhtalbihu Beda a kwi Sherk-Siam </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">tuhuyutcut 툾aci톫talbix퉝 b톛da 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">past made+self man son of+the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">The Son of God made himself a man</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                    
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual kwi gwas trotobolhs tolal ku tskwadadchelh eku tolal ku gwed hud eba dhual kwi gwas ortobolhs duhsherk. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">dx퉝툾al k퉝i g퉝톛stx팳퉝utubu톫s tul퉢툾al k퉝i 퉋톛k퉢퉝adadc팳톛톫  툾i k퉝i tul퉢툾al k퉝i g퉝톛d hud 툾ib톛 dx퉝툾al k퉝i g퉝톛s툾ux팳퉝utubu톫s d톛x퉝ss팳톛q.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">unto the IRREAL pull+us from the sin+us and+the from the IRREAL fire</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">in order to pull us from our sins and from the fire and in order to make us ascend to heaven.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                                
      <l n="16">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">7. To abijtobolh o ku Shesu-Kri aku tus atebeds al lekwe ?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">7. tu툾abyitubu톫 툾u k퉝i Shesu-Kri 툾톛 k퉝i tus툾at톛b톛ds 툾al l톛kw톛.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">7. past receive Q the Jesus Christ the past death on the+cross</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">7. Was Jesus Christ put to death on the cross?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                                    
      <l n="17">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, tu abijtobolh ku Shesu-Kri a ku tus atebeds al lekwe.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, tu툾abyitubu톫 k퉝i Shesu-Kri 툾톛 k퉝i tus툾at톛b톛ds 툾al l톛kw톛.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes, past receive the Jesus Christ the past death on the+cross</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, Jesus Christ was put to death on the cross.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                                        
      <l n="18">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">8. Tu atebed o kwi Shesu-Kri al stselatselh datils gula tu palil o al raraalhdat?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">8. tu툾at톛b톛d 툾u k퉝i Shesu-Kri 툾al c톛lac톛톫datils g퉝톛l tup팻alil 툾u 툾al x팳a툾x팳a툾톛톫dat.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">8. died Q the Jesus-Christ on fifth-day then regain_consciousness Q on holy_day</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">8. Did Jesus die on Friday and did He resurrect on Sunday?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                                            
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo"> E, tu atebed ku Shesu-Kri al stselatselh datils gula tu palil al raraalhdat.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, tu툾at톛b톛d k퉝i Shesu-Kri 툾al c톛lac톛톫datils g퉝톛l tup팻alil 툾al x팳a툾x팳a툾톛톫dat.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes died Q the Jesus-Christ on fifth-day then regain_consciousness on holy_day</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, Jesus did die on Friday and resurrect on Sunday.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                                                
      <l n="20">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">9. Sbosache o slar^el ku tus als swatihuhted Shesu-Kri tolal ku tus palils gula tu orduhsherk?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">9. sbuusac팳i툾 툾u sl톛x팳il k퉝i tus툾als swatix퉝t톛d Shesu-Kri tul퉢툾al k퉝i tusp팻alils g퉝톛l tu툾ux팳퉝dx퉝s팳톛q.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">9. forty Q days the past be world Jesus Christ from the revival+his then past go+up+heaven</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">9. Was Jesus Christ on the earth for forty days from when he resurrected and then ascended to heaven?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                                                        
      <l n="21">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, sbosache slar칡l ku tus als swatihuhted Shesu-Kri tolal ku tus palils gula tu orduhsherk.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾톛, sbuusac팳i툾 sl톛x팳il k퉝i tus툾als swatihuht톛d Shesu-Kri tul퉢툾al k퉝i tusp팻alils g퉝톛l  tu툾ux팳퉝dx퉝s팳톛q.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes forty days the past be world Jesus Christ from the revival+his then past go+up+heaven</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, Jesus Christ was on the earth for forty days from when he resurrected and then ascended to heaven.</rdg>                            
        </app></l>          
                                                                                                
      <l n="22">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">10. Olob o slar칡l tolal ku tus ors duhsherk Shesu-Kri gula tu chiss칙d ku Sent-Ospli dhual elesapot? </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">10. 툾ulub 툾u sl톛x팳il tul퉢툾al k퉝i tu툾x팳퉝dx퉝s팳톛q Shesu-Kri g퉝톛l tuc팳톛sad k퉝i Sent-Ospli dx퉝툾al 툾톛 lesapot.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">10. ten Q days from the go+up Jesus+Christ then sent the Holy+Spirit unto the apostles</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">10. Was it ten days after His ascension to heaven that He sent the Holy Spirit to the apostles?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                                                                        
      <l n="23">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, olob slar칡l tolal ku tus ors duhsherk Shesu-Kri gula tu chiss칙d ku Sent-Ospli dhual elesapot.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i,  툾ulub sl톛x팳il tul퉢툾al k퉝i tu툾ux팳퉝sdx퉝s팳톛q  s팳hesu-kli g퉝톛l tuc팳톛sad k퉝i s톛nt-Ospli dx퉝툾al 툾톛 lesapot.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes ten Q days from the go+up Jesus+Christ then sent the Holy+Spirit unto the apostles</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, it was ten days after His ascension to heaven that He sent the Holy Spirit to the apostles.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>