<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit catéchisme des indiens", 8e leçon -->
    
    <body>
        <p>LESSON I. </p>
          
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Stab tihîlh tskwadad?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. stab tiʔiɬ dᶻəkʼʷadad?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. What is sin?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tihîlh spetîdegwasseb, tihîlh sgwadgwad, tihîlh siayus, tihîlh whe la duhsiayus, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">tiʔiɬ spətidgʷasəb, tiʔiɬ sgʷadgʷad, tiʔiɬ syayus, tiʔiɬ xʷiʔ lədəxʷsyayus,</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">A thought, a saying, a deed, something not done,</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                      
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">abil whe la tsoku dhual di Sherk-Siam, gula dilh tskwadad.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔabil xʷiʔ ləcəkʼʷ dxʷʔal diʔ šəq siʔab, gʷəl diʔɬ dᶻəkʼʷadad.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">if it is not right unto the sky nobleman, then it is sin.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                            
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Whe o ku dcho tskwadad al debalh aku tus wollechelh?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. xʷiʔ ʔu kʷi dəč'uʔ dᶻəkʼʷadad ʔal dibəɬ ʔə kʷi tuswəliʔčəɬ.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. Is there not one sin of ours when we appeared?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                  
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, al ku tus wollechelh, aku dcho tskwadad al debalh tolal Adam.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi, ʔal kʷi tuswəliʔčəɬ, ʔaʔ kʷi dəč'uʔ dᶻəkʼʷadad ʔal dibəɬ tulʼʔal Adam.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, at our appearance there was one sin with us from Adam.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                        
      <l n="6">
         <app>
           <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Whe o ku sales ku siayus aku atsilhtalbihu lalegwas tskwadad;</rdg>
           <rdg wit="#BL">3. xʷiʔ ʔu kʷi saliʔs kʷi syayus ʔə kʷi ʔaciɬtalbixʷ ləliʔgʷas dᶻəkʼʷadad;</rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#LG">3. Are  there two ways of making the people different sins?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                              
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">dcho ku duhsatebedid ku sele, gula dcho ku hoyud asralh ku sele?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">dəč'uʔ kʷi dəxʷsʔatəbədid kʷi sələ, gʷəl dəč'uʔ kʷi huyud ʔəsx̌əɬ kʷi shəliʔ.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">one that makes the soul mortal, then one that make the soul sick</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                    
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, sale ku soyayus aku atsilhtalbihu lalegwas tskwadad, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi, saliʔ kʷi suyayus ʔə kʷi ʔaciɬtalbixʷ ləliʔgʷas dᶻəkʼʷadad, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes,  there are two ways of making the people different sins</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                          
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">dcho ku o atebedid ku sele, gula dcho ku o hoyud asralh ku sele.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">dəč'uʔ kʷi ʔuʔatəbədid kʷi shəliʔ, gʷəl dəč'uʔ kʷi ʔuhuyud ʔəsx̌əɬ kʷi shəliʔ.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">one that makes the soul mortal, then one that make the soul sick</rdg>
        </app></l>

            
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>