<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit cat칠chisme des indiens", pp. 428-429 -->
    <!-- http://eucharisticadoration.com/articles/36/1/Baltimore-Catechism-4/Page1.html helped a lot too -->
    
    <body>
        <p>LESSON II.</p>
            
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Stab tih칥lh Lokaristi?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. stab ti툾i톫 Lokaristi.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">1. what  the eucharist</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. What is the eucharist?</rdg> 
        </app></l>
            
          
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tihilh Lokaristi dcho Sakrema aku tsokwab eku stolegwad gwalh Shesu-Kri askro, aku tsid칥lh Shesu-Kri boku.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ti툾i톫 Lokaristi d톛c팳'u툾 Sakrema 툾톛 k퉝i c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b 툾i k퉝i stulig퉝톛d g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri 툾톛sq퉢퉝u툾, 툾톛 k퉝i c톛di톫 Shesu-Kri b톛k퉢퉝.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">the eucharist one sacrament of the body and the blood belonging_to Jesus_Christ together of the that Jesus_Christ all</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">The eucharist is a sacrament of the body and the blood of Jesus Christ together, of the entire Jesus Christ.</rdg> 
        </app></l>
            
              
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe gwa stab gwa saplel, dayai srwekrokus saplels, eta stlokos saplels, eta saplel alakrops.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">x퉝i툾 g퉝톛stab g퉝톛saplil, day퉢ay퉢 sq퉝톛q퉢퉝us saplils, 툾i t톛 s톫a툾x팳us saplils, 툾i t톛 saplil 툾톛 l톛k퉢퉝톛bs.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">not much bread only white bread and the round bread and the bread of eaten</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Not a lot of bread, only white bread, and round bread, and edible bread.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                      
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Dilh dahu as gwalh Shesu-Kri tsokwab eta boku Shesu-Kri askro. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">di톫 d톛x퉝톛s g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b 툾i t톛 b톛k퉢퉝 Shesu-Kri 툾톛sq퉢퉝u툾 .</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">that way belonging_to Jesus_Christ body and the all Jesus_Christ together</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">That is how the body of Jesus Christ and Jesus Christ entire.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                          
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe gwa stab gwa wain dayai gwalh wain rlhte kro, eta gwalh wain skwalhs, etas wain alakrops. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">x퉝i툾 g퉝톛stab g퉝톛wain day퉢ay퉢 g퉝톛톫 wain x팳톛톫 ti q퉢퉝u툾 , 툾i t톛 g퉝톛톫 wain sk퉢퉝톛톫s,  툾i t톛 swain 툾톛 l톛k퉢퉝톛bs.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LG">not much wine only belonging_to wine seems the water and IRR wine pouring and the wine of ingestible </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">A little bit of wine only, water that looks like wine, and pouring some wine, and drinkable wine.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                              
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Dilh dahu as gwalh Shesu-Kri stolegwad, eta boku Shesi-Kri askro.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">di톫 d톛x퉝톛s g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri stulig퉝톛d, 툾i t톛 b톛k퉢퉝 Shesu-kri 툾톛sq퉢퉝u툾.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">that how IRR Jesus_Christ blood and the entire Jesus Christ together</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">That is how the blood of Jesus Christ, and the entire Jesus Christ together.</rdg>
        </app></l>
           
            
                                  
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Alchad kus o hoyutobs lale aku leple ku saplel gwa tla hoyil gwalh Shesu-Kri tsokwab, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. 툾al c팳ad s툾uhuyut톛bs l톛li툾 툾톛 k퉝i leple k퉝i saplil g퉝톛톫uhuyil g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LWG">2. at where made other by the priest the bread change belonging_to Jesus_Christ's body</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. Where is the bread changed into Jesus Christ's body by the priest?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                      
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">'tlalba alchad kus o hoyutobs lale aku leple ku wain gwa tla hoyil gwalh Shesu-Kri stolegwad?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL"> 쿹'al퉢b톛 툾al c팳ad k퉝i s툾uhuyut톛bs l톛li툾 툾톛 k퉝i l톛pl톛 k퉝i  wain  g퉝톛톫uhuyil  g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri stulig퉝톛d?</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">and at where the made other by the priest the wine made belonging_to Jesus_Christ blood</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and where is the wine changed into Jesus Christ's blood by the priest?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                          
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al lames kus o hoyutobs lale aku leple ku saplel gwa tla hoyil gwalh Shesu-Kri tsokwab, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾al lam톛s  k퉝i suhuyut톛bs l톛li툾 툾톛 k퉝i l톛pl톛 k퉝i saplil g퉝톛톫uhuyil gw톛톫Shesu-Kri c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b, </rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">at mass the making other by the priest the bread changed belonging_to Jesus Christ body</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">At the mass is where the bread is changed into Jesus Christ's body by the priest</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                              
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo"> 'tlalba al lames kus o hoyutobs lale aku leple ku wain, gwa tla hoyil gwalh Shesu-Kri stolegwad.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">쿹'al퉢b톛 툾al lames  k퉝i suhuyut톛bs l톛li툾 툾톛 k퉝i leple k퉝i wain, g퉝톛톫uhuyil g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri stulig퉝톛d</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">and at mass the made other by the priest the wine changed belonging_to Jesus_Christ blood</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and at the mass is where the wine is changed into Jesus Christ's blood by the priest.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
                                                  
      <l n="12">
                                                    
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Stab tih칥lh lames?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">3. stab  ti툾i톫 lames.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">3. what the mass</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">3. What is the mass?</rdg>   
        </app></l>
            
                                                      
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tih칥lh lames gwalh Shesu-Kri tsokwab, eku stolegwad tu sabijobs, rolab aku tu dhual lekwe. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL"> ti툾i톫 lames g퉝톛톫 Shesu-Kri c퉢uk퉢퉝톛b, 툾i k퉝i stulig퉝톛d tus툾abiyit톛bs, x팳퉝ul퉢ab 툾톛 k퉝i tudx퉝툾al lekwe.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">The mass is the body of Christ and the blood gotten only ??????? on the cross.</rdg>   
        </app></l>
            
                                                          
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">4. Asared ku tlo alaluschelh al kus lames?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">4. 툾톛s툾톛x팳id k퉝i 톫u툾alalusc팳톛톫 툾al k퉝si lames.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">4. how the behave+we at the mass</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">4. How should we behave at the mass?</rdg>   
        </app></l>
            
                                                              
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tlo achelh al kus lames aku halh, tlo tegwidchelh di Sherk-Siam tlo pet칡degwassebchelh aku tsoku, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">톫u툾a툾c팳톛톫 툾al k퉝si lames 툾톛 k퉝i ha툾톫, 톫ut퉢ig퉝id c팳톛톫 di s팳톛q si툾ab 톫up톛tidg퉝as톛bc팳톛톫 툾톛 k퉝i c톛k퉝,</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LWG">be+we at the mass of the good FUT pray+we the sky nobleman thinking+we  of the correct</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LG">We should be good at the mass, we pray to God that our thoughts be correct,</rdg>   
        </app></l>
            
                                                                  
      <l n="16">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula whe kwi tlo sogukrtsutchelh aku pa'tla'tl. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">g퉝톛l x퉝i툾 k퉝i 톫ug톛q퉢cutc팳톛톫 툾톛 k퉝i p퉢a쿹퉢a쿹퉢. </rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then not the open+self+we of the foolishness</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">and we don't open ourselves up to foolishness</rdg> 
        </app></l>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>