<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit cat칠chisme des indiens", 3e le칞on -->
    
    <body>
        <p>LESSON IV. </p>
            
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Kraa o kwi Sherk-Siam?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. x팳a툾 툾u k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LWG">1. many Q the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. Are there many gods?</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe la kraa kwi Sherk-Siam, rol diecho kwi Sherk-Siam.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">x퉝i툾 l톛x팳a툾 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab, x팳퉝ul퉢 d톛c팳'u툾 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LWG">not many the sky nobleman, only one the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">There are not many gods, there is only one God.</rdg>
        </app></l>
            
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Kraa o kwi parson al kwi Sherk-Siam?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. x팳a툾 툾u k퉝i parson 툾al k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">2. many Q the person in the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. Are there many persons in God?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                        
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tlewhehu parson al kwi Sherk-Siam: Bads, Bedas, Sent-Ospli.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">톫ix퉝톛x퉝 parson 툾al k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab: bads, b톛da툾s, Sent-Ospli.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">three person in the sky nobleman: Father, Son, Holy Spirit</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">There are three persons in God: the Father, the Son, the Holy Spirit.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                              
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Bads o rol o Bads, Bedas o rol o Bedas, Sent-Ospli o rol o Sent-Ospli?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">3. bads 툾u x팳퉝ul퉢 툾u bads, b톛da툾s 툾u x팳퉝ul퉢 툾u b톛da툾s, Sent-Ospli 툾u x팳퉝ul퉢 Sent-Ospli.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">3. father Q only Q father, son Q only Q son, holy-spirit Q only holy-spirit</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">3. Is the Father only the Father, is the Son only the Son, is the Holy Spirit only the Holy Spirit?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                    
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, Bads hoi rol Bads, Bedas hoi rol Bedas, Sent-Ospli hoi rol Sent-Ospli. </rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, bads huy x팳퉝ul퉢 bads, b톛da툾s huy x팳퉝ul퉢 b톛da툾s, Sent-Ospli huy x팳퉝ul퉢 Sent-Ospli.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes father well only father, son well only son, holy-spirit well only holy-spirit</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, the Father is only the Father, the Son is only the Son, the Holy Spirit is only the Holy Spirit.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                          
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">4. Bads, Bedas, Sent-Ospli, tlewhehu o ta tsahadilh parson, tor o rol diecho Sherk-Siam?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">4. bads, b톛das, Sent-Ospli, 톫ix퉝톛x퉝 툾u t톛 c톛di톫 parson, tux팳퉝 툾u x팳퉝ul퉢 d톛c팳'u툾 s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">4. father, son, holy spirit, three Q the them person, simply Q one sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">4. Are the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit three persons, are they just only one God?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, Bad, Bedas, Sent-Ospli, tlewhehu ta tsahadilh parson dididiecho, tor rol diecho Sherk-Siam.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, bad, b톛da툾s, Sent-Ospli,  톫ix퉝톛x퉝 t톛 c톛di톫 parson didid톛c'u툾, tux팳퉝 x팳퉝ul퉢 d톛c팳'u툾 s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes, Father, Son, holy spirit, three the them person one-by-one, simply only one sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are three separate persons, and are just only one God.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                      
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">5. Telh o Bads, Bedas, Sent-Ospli, rol lekralgwas dhual kwi boku stab?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">5. t톛톫 툾u bads, b톛da툾s, Sent-Ospli, x팳퉝ul퉢 l톛x팳alg퉝as dx퉝툾al k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 stab툾</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">5. true Q father, son, holy spirit, only equal above the all things</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">5. Is it true that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit alone are equal above all things?</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                            
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, telh Bads, Bedas, Sent-Ospli, rol lekralgwas dhual kwi boku stab.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, t톛톫 bads, b톛da툾s, Sent-Ospli, x팳퉝ul퉢 l톛x팳alg퉝as dx퉝툾al k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 stab.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes, true father, son, holy spirit, only equal above the all things</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, it is true that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit alone are equal above all things?</rdg>
        </app></l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>