<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit cat茅chisme des indiens", 6e le莽on -->
    
    <body>
        <p>LESSON VII. </p>
            
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Telh o as oshakitob a kwi Sherk-Siam ku atsilhtalbihu dhual ku tskwadads halgwa? </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. t蓹涩 蕯u g史蓹蕯us虒蓹bit蓹b 蕯蓹 k史i s虒蓹q si蕯ab k史i 蕯aci涩talbix史 dx史蕯al k史i d岫簧檏始史adads h蓹lg史蓹蕯.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">1. true Q mercy of the sky nobleman the people toward the sins their</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. Is it true that God has mercy on the people because of their sins?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, abil' gwat gwa rahab tolal ku tskwadads, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL"> 蕯i, 蕯蓹bil始  g史at  g史蓹x虒ah蓹b  tul始al k史i d岫簧檏始史adads, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes if somebody cries about the sin+his</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, if a person repents of their sins,</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gwa asra'tledhu kwi gwas hoyils halh; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL"> g史蓹sx虒虒a茮'蓹dx史 k史i g史蓹shuyils ha蕯涩; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">want the make good</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and make themselves good</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                        
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula telh gwa oshabitob a Sherk-Siam dhual ku tskwadads. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">g史蓹l t蓹涩 g史蓹蕯us虒蓹bit蓹b 蕯蓹 s虒蓹q si蕯ab dx史蕯al k史i d岫簧檏始史adads.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then truly mercy of the sky nobleman unto the sins+his</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">then God will indeed have mercy on his sins.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                              
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Abil o gwat ahus hoyudab whe ku tskwadads dhual di Sherk-Siam, gula stab kwi gwa siayus?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. 蕯蓹bil始 蕯u g史at蓹x史s huyud蓹b  x史i蕯 k史i d岫簧檏始史adads dx史蕯al di蕯 s虒蓹q si蕯ab, g史蓹l stab k史i g史蓹syayus.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">2. perhaps Q who done not the sin unto the sky nobleman then what the work</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. Who perhaps has not done any sin unto God then what will he do?</rdg>
        </app></l>         
                                          
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Abil gwat ahus hoyudab whe ku tskwadads dhual di Sherk-Siam, gula kudad ku stsaiku; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯蓹bil始 g史at蓹x史s huyud蓹b x史i蕯 k史i d岫簧檏始史adads dx史蕯al di蕯 s虒蓹q si蕯ab, g史蓹l k史蓹dad  k史i sc虝a蕯k史;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then what done not the sin unto that sky nobleman, then take the baptism</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">abil gwat astsaku gula gwa yayus aku tsaku dhual rarasmilalam.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯蓹bil始 g史at 蕯蓹sc虝a蕯k史  g史蓹l g史蓹yayus 蕯蓹 k史i sc虝a蕯k史 dx史蕯al x虒虒a蕯x虒虒虒a蕯sbillala蕯蓹b.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">if someone baptized then works of the baptism??? to confession</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                      
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Abil o Sherk-Siam gwa oshabid ku atsilhtalbihu dhual ku tskwadads halgwa, gula gwa hoyil o halh ku seles halgwa?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">3. 蕯蓹bil始 蕯u  s虒蓹q si蕯ab  g史蓹蕯us虒蓹bid k史i 蕯aci涩talbix史 dx史蕯al k史i d岫簧檏始史adads h蓹lg史蓹蕯, g史蓹l  g史蓹huyil 蕯u ha蕯涩 k史i sh蓹li蕯s h蓹lg史蓹蕯.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">3. perhaps Q sky nobleman save the people from the sins their then make Q good the souls their</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">3. Will God perhaps save the people from their sins and make their soul good?</rdg>
        </app></l>       
                                                                  
      <l n="11">                                                                    
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, abil Sherk-Siam gwa oshabid ku atsilhtalbihu dhual ku tskwadads halgwa, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯i, 蕯蓹bil始 s虒蓹q si蕯ab g史蓹蕯us虒蓹bid k史i 蕯aciltalbix史 dx史蕯al k史i d岫簧檏始史adads h蓹lg史蓹蕯, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes, perhaps sky nobleman save the people from the sins their</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, perhaps God will save the people from their sins</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                        
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula gwa bechad ku sgwas sabalekus dhual ku sales halgwa,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">g史蓹l g史蓹b蓹c虒ad k史i sg史a蕯s s蕯abalik史s dx史蕯al k史i sh蓹li蕯s h蓹lg史蓹蕯,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then ??? ??? ??? unto the life their</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                              
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gwla asista gwa dahu hois halh ku seles halgwa.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">g史蓹l 蕯蓹s蕯ist蓹蕯 g史蓹dx史huys ha蕯涩 k史i sh蓹li蕯s h蓹lg史蓹蕯.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then this way+make good the souls their</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and this is how he will make their souls good.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>