<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG"/>
          <witness xml:id="LG"/>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- very similar to Zenk's "Petit cat칠chisme des Indiens", 1ere le칞on -->
    
    <body>
        <p>LESSON II.</p>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Stab kwi Sherk-Siam ?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. stab k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LWG">1. what the heaven nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. What is God?</rdg>
        </app></l>

      <l n="2">
        <app> 
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Rol rech kwi Sherk-Siam whe la asared gwas haiduhcheh asared kwis halh a kwi Sherk-Siam.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">x팳퉝ul퉢 x팳톛c팳 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab x퉝i툾 l톛툾톛s툾톛x팳id g퉝톛shaydx퉝c팳톛톫 툾톛s툾톛x팳id k퉝i sha툾톫 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">only spirit the sky nobleman not how know+we how the goodness of the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">God is merely spirit; we are not able to know how much is the goodness of God.</rdg>
        </app></l>
          
            
                      
      <l n="3">
        <app>  
          <rdg wit="#Bo"> 2. Abstsokwab o kwi Sherk-Siam, rwekokru o, rebech o?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. absc퉢uk퉢퉝톛b 툾u k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab, x팳퉝톛q퉝톛q퉢퉝 툾u, x팳ib톛c팳' 툾u.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">2 has+body Q the sky nobleman, white Q, black Q</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG"> Does God have a body? Is He white? Is He black?</rdg>
        </app></l>
          
      <l n="4">     
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe la abstsokwab kwi Sherk-Siam, whe la rwekokru whe la rebech.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">x퉝i툾 l톛툾absc퉢uk퉢퉝톛b k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab, x퉝i툾 l톛x팳퉝톛q퉝톛q퉢퉝 x퉝i툾 l톛x팳ib톛c팳'.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LWG"> not have+body the sky nobleman, not white, not black</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG"> He does not have a body. He is not white, He isn't black.</rdg>
        </app></l>
    
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Tskwakred o a kwi Sherk-Siam ?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL"> 3. ck퉢퉝aqid 툾u 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG"> 3. forever Q of the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG"> 3. Is God eternal?</rdg>
        </app></l>

      <l n="6">
        <app>             
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, tskwakred a kwi Sherk-Siam, tolal ku di tu haku tskwakred a kwi Sherk-Siam a al tih칥lh i kwi tlhba tskwakred tlus as.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, ck퉢퉝aqid 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab, tul퉢툾al k퉝톛di툾 tuha툾k퉝 ck퉢퉝aqid 툾톛 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab 툾a 툾al ti툾i톫 툾i k퉝i 톫톛b톛ck퉢퉝aqid 톫us툾a툾s.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG"> yes forever of the sky nobleman, from the long_ago forever of the sky nobleman exist to the and the future+forever future+exist</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG"> Yes, God is eternal, from the remote past God always existed, He exists now, and He will always exist.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                 
      <l n="7">        
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">4. Boku o dahu as kwi boku lilhchad kwi Sherk-Siam, gula boku o ashuts kwi bokw stab? </rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">4. b톛k퉢퉝 툾u d톛x퉝툾as k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 li톫c팳ad k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab, g퉝톛l b톛k퉢퉝 툾u 툾톛shuyuc  k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 stab?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG"> 4. all Q means the all which+way the sky nobleman, then all Q made the all thing</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">4. ??? and did he make everything that was made?</rdg>
        </app></l>
          
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, boku dahu as kwi boku lilhchad kwi Sherk-Siam, gula boku ashuts kwi boku stab.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">툾i, b톛k퉢퉝 d톛x퉝툾as k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 li톫c팳ad k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab, g퉝톛l b톛k퉢퉝 툾톛shuyuc k퉝i b톛k퉢퉝 stab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG"> yes all means the all which+way the sky nobleman, then all made the all thing</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, ??? and did he make everything that was made.</rdg>
        </app></l>

      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">5. Whe la asared o gwas haiduhchelh asared kwerkru kwi Sherk-Siam?</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">5. x퉝i툾 l톛툾톛s툾톛x팳id 툾u g퉝톛shaydx퉝c팳톛톫 툾톛s툾톛x팳id q퉝iq퉢퉝 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">5. not how Q IRR+know+us how powerful the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">5. Aren't we able to know how powerful God is?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe la asared gwas haiduhchelh asared kwerkru kwi Sherk-Siam; </rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">x퉝i툾 l톛툾톛s툾톛x팳id g퉝톛shaydx퉝c팳톛톫 툾톛s툾톛x팳id q퉝iq퉢퉝 k퉝i s팳톛q si툾ab</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">not how IRR+know+us how powerful the sky nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">We are not able to know how powerful God is;</rdg>
        </app></l>
                  
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">yare boku stab kria dhual tsid칥lh.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#BL">y톛x팳i b톛k퉢퉝 stab kria dx퉝툾al c톛di톫</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">but all things rien=nothing unto him</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">but all things are nothing unto him.</rdg>
        </app></l>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>