<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit catéchisme des indiens", 5e leçon -->
    
    <body>
        <p>LESSON VI.</p>
            
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1. Stab tihîlh leglis?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. stab tiʔiɬ ləglis ?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">1. what the church</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. What is the church?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tihîlh leglis skrokro gwalh boku tsoku kretia tolal boku lilhched;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">tiʔiɬ ləglis sqʼʷuʔqʼʷuʔ gʷəɬ bəkʷ cəkʷ kretia tulʼʔal bəkʼʷ liɬčəd;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">the church gathering belonging-to all straight christians from all which-way</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">The church is a gathering of all true Christians from everywhere</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                  
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">sgwas halgwa lilhzihu sihusiams halgwa Shesu-Kri al di sherk; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">sgʷaʔs həlgʷə liɬʤixʷ sixʷsiʔabs həlgʷə Shesu-Kri ʔal diʔ šəq;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">their-own they first high+nobleman Jesus Christ in the sky</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">their own first leader is Jesus Christ in heaven</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                        
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula lepam lilhzihu sihusiams halgwa al ku swatihuhted. </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">gʷəl lepam liɬʤixʷ sixʷsiʔabs həlgʷə ʔal kʷi swatixʷtəd.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then the-pope first high+nobleman their on the earth</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">then the pope is their first leader on the earth</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                              
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Shesu-Kri o ku tu hoyud lepam lilhzihu Siam? </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. Shesu-Kri ʔu kʷi tuhuyud lepam liɬʤixʷ siʔab.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">2. Jesus Christ Q the past made pope first nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. Was it Jesus Christ who made the pope the first leader?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                    
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, Shesu-Kri ku tu hoyud ku lepam lilhzibu Siam, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi, Shesu-Kri  kʷi tuhuyud kʷi lepam  liɬʤixʷ siʔab, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes Jesus Christ the past made pope first nobleman</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, it was Jesus Christ who made the pope the first leader,</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                          
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula tsidîlh Sen-Piel tu hoyil lilhizihu lepam.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">gʷəl cədiɬ Sen-Piel tuhuyil liɬʤixʷ ləpam .</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then it-was Saint-Peter made first pope</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and it was Saint Peter who was made the first pope.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                                
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Tsidîlh o Shesu-Kri ku tu hoyud siam ku lesebek?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">3.  cədiɬ ʔu Shesu-Kri kʷi tuhuyud siʔab kʷi lesebek.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">3. them Q Jesus Christ the past made nobleman the bishops</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">3. Was it Jesus Christ who made the bishops leaders?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                                      
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, tsidîlh Shesu-Kri tu hoyud siam ku lesebek, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi, cədiɬ Shesu-Kri tuhuyud siʔab kʷi lesebek ,  </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes. them Jesus Christ the past made nobleman the bishops</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, it was Jesus Christ who made the bishops leaders?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                                            
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gwla lepam sihusiam aku lesebek; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">gʷəl lepam sixʷsiʔab ʔə kʷi lesebek;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">and pope highest+nobleman of the bishops</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and the pope the leader of the bishops.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
      <l n="11">                                                              
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula tsahadilh lesapot ku tu hoyil lilhzihu lesebek.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">gʷəl caadiɬ lesapot kʷi tuhuyil liɬʤixʷ lesebek .</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then those apostles the made first bishops</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and the apostles made the first bishops.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                                                        
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">4. Tsidîlh o Shesu-Kri ku tu hoyud ku leple,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">4.  cədiɬ ʔu Shesu-Kri kʷi tuhuyud kʷi leple, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">4. Q Jesus-Christ the made the priests</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Was it Jesus Christ who made the priests</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
                                                                              
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual kwi gwa dahu haidubtobus ku atsilhtalbihu, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">dxʷʔal kʷi gʷədəxʷ haydubtubus kʷi ʔaciltalbixʷ, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">for the way-to know?? the people</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">as a way to get to know the people</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                    
      <l n="14">      
        <app>                                   
          <rdg wit="#Bo">eba dhual kwi gwas hoyuds halh?</rdg>                                    
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔibə dxʷʔal kʷi gʷəshuyuds haʔɬ.</rdg>         
          <rdg wit="#LWG">and for the do good</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and to do good?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                          
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">E, tsidîlh Shesu-Kri ku tu hoyud ku leple, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi, cədiɬ Shesu-Kri kʷi tuhʷyud kʷi  leple , </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">yes Jesus-Christ the made the priests</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">Yes, it was Jesus Christ who made the priests</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                
      <l n="16">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">dhual kwi gwa dahu haidubtobus ku atsilhtalbihu, eba dhual kwi gwas hoyuds halh; </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">dxʷʔal kʷi gʷədəxʷhaydubtubus kʷi ʔaciɬtalbixʷ, ʔibə dxʷʔal kʷi gʷəshuyuds haʔɬ;  </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">for the way-to know?? the people and for the do good</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">as a way to get to know the people and to do good.</rdg>
        </app></l>
    
            
                                                                                                            
      <l n="18">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula tihîlh lepam eku lesebek sihusiams halgwa.</rdg>       
          <rdg wit="#BL">gʷəl tiʔiɬ lepam  ʔi kʷi  lesebek sixʷsiʔabs həlgʷə.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">then the pope and the bishops leaders their</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">and the pope and the bishops are their leaders.</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                                  
      <l n="19">     
        <app>                     
          <rdg wit="#Bo">5. Whe o la asared gwas za'tlab aku leglis al tihîlh sogutsiebalhs?</rdg>                 
          <rdg wit="#BL">5. xʷiʔ ʔu ləʔəsʔəx̌id gʷəsʤaƛʼab ʔə kʷi ləglis ʔal ti?iɬ sʔugʷəcyəbaɬs?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">5. not Q why mistaken the church in the teachings</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">5. Can't it happen that the church could err in its teachings?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                                        
      <l n="20">       
        <app>         
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Whe la asared gwas za'tlab aku leglis al tihîlh sogutsiebalhs, yare tskwakred a al tsidîlh ku Sent-Ospli.</rdg>                                                
          <rdg wit="#BL">xʷiʔ ləʔəsʔəx̌id gʷəsʤaƛʼab ʔə kʷi ləglis ʔal ti?iɬ sʔugʷucəbaɬs, yəx̌i ckʼʷaqid ʔaʔ ʔal cədiɬ kʷi Sent-Ospli.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">not why mistaken of the church in the teachings because always there of that the holy spirit</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">It can't happen that the church could err in its teachings because the Holy Spirit is always there.</rdg>
        </app></l>
                                                                                                                                    
      <l n="22">
        <app>                                          
          <rdg wit="#Bo"> 6. Stab tihîlh lakomion desa?</rdg>                                                
          <rdg wit="#BL">6. stab tiʔiɬ lakomion desa. </rdg>      
          <rdg wit="#LWG">6. what the communion of-the-saints</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">6. What is the communion of the saints?</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="23">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tihîlh lakomion desa sahu abietagwalh aku gwalh sele stabegus </rdg>    
          <rdg wit="#BL">tiʔiɬ  lakomion dəsa səxʷʔabyitagʷəɬ ʔə kʷi gʷəl shəliʔ stabigʷs </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">the communion of-the-saints giving-each-other of the of life possession</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">The communion of the saints is giving each other of those possessing life</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                                                                
      <l n="24">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">al ku tsoku kretia al ku swatihuhted </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔal kʷi cəkʷ kretia ʔal kʷi swatixʷtəd </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">of the true christians in the world</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">of the true christians in the world</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="25">
        <app>  
          <rdg wit="#Bo"> eta ba dhual ku halh skayu al di sherk, </rdg>         
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi tə bədəxʷ ʔal kʷi haʔɬ skayuʔ ʔal diʔ šəq, </rdg>     
          <rdg wit="#LWG">and the ??? of the good dead in the heaven</rdg>
        </app></l>
      
            
                                                                                                                                                            
      <l n="26">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">eta ba dhual ta tsahadîlh askrpaleku halgwa al pikatwar.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#BL">ʔi bədəxʷ ʔal tə  cəədiɬ ʔəsqəpalikʷ həlgʷəʔ ʔal pikatwar.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LWG">and the ??? their in purgatory</rdg>
        </app></l>
      

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>