<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../src/vmachineDWL.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader><fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc><encodingDesc> 
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
    </encodingDesc></teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Bo">Boulet</witness>
          <witness xml:id="BL">Bates and Lonsdale</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LWG">Lonsdale word gloss</witness>
          <witness xml:id="LG">Lonsdale gloss</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>
    
    <!-- similar to Zenk's "Petit cat茅chisme des indiens", p. 420+ -->
    
    <body>
      <p>LESSON IV.</p>
        
      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">1.Stab tih卯lh Lapelitas?  </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">1. stab ti蕯i涩 Lapelitas.</rdg>     
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. What is penitence蕯</rdg> 
        </app></l>
        
          
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Tih卯lh Lapelitas dcho Sakrema ohoyud whe gwalh kretia tskwadad.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">ti蕯i涩 Lapelitas  d蓹c虒'u蕯 Sakrema 蕯uhuyud x史i蕯 g史蓹涩 kretia d岫簧檏始史adad.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">1. Penitence is a sacrament that makes null the sin of a Christian.</rdg> 
        </app></l>
        
              
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">2. Stab tihilh rarasmilalam?</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">2. stab ti蕯i涩 x虒ax虒a sbil始蕯alla蕯蓹b.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LG">2. What is confession蕯</rdg> 
        </app></l>
        
                  
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Abil gwat kretia ohaidhuthu  ku leple aku boku tskwadads dahu hoyils whe ku tskwadads, gula dilh rarasmilalam.  </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯蓹bil始 g史at kretia 蕯uhaydx史tx史 k史i leple 蕯蓹 k史i b蓹k始史 d岫簧檏始史adads d蓹x史huyils x史i蕯 k史i d岫簧檏始史adads, g史蓹l di涩 x虒ax虒a sbil始蕯alla蕯蓹b.</rdg>    
          <rdg wit="#LG">When a Christian makes known to the priest all of his sins in order to make null his sin, that is holy confession.</rdg>
        </app></l> 
        
                      
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">3. Asared kwi tla ad'skwebitsut dhual ku rarasmilalam?</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">3. 蕯蓹s蕯蓹x虒id k史i 涩adsq史ibcut dx史蕯al k史i x虒ax虒a sbil始蕯alla蕯蓹b.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">3. How do you prepare yourself for the holy confession?</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                          
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Zihu kwi tla dstehech dhual di Sherk-Siam, tlhdahu kwawhats, lakrahu ched tla eidhu, ched tla reched ku dtskwadad; </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">d岫籭x史 k史i 涩udstihic虒 dx史蕯al di蕯 s虒蓹q si蕯ab, t涩dx史 k史ax史ac, ???  c虒蓹d 涩u蕯蓹ydx史, c虒蓹d 涩ux虒蓹c虒蓹d k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad;</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">First you pray unto God, truly to take ??? I will make known, I will think about my sin;</rdg>
        </app></l> 
        
                              
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">al slewhatlels ched tla dhu stsotab al ku drech:</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al s涩ix史a涩ils c虒蓹d 涩udx史scut蓹b 蕯al k史i dx虒蓹c虒:</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                  
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">telh halh kwi Sherk-Siam ra'tltobsh ti tsa, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">t蓹涩 ha蕯涩 k史i s虒蓹q si蕯ab x虒虒a茮'tubs虒 ti 蕯蓹ca,</rdg>     
          <rdg wit="#LG">truly good is my desire toward God </rdg> 
        </app></l>
        
                                      
      <l n="9">
        <app>
           <rdg wit="#Bo">whe la ra'tlthu kwi gwa desor dohugwad; </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">x史i蕯 l蓹x虒虒a茮'tx史 k史i _gwad蓹sor_??? d蓹x史蕯ug史ad; </rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                          
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">tor ched tu whobed ku sgwas schelhrechems, tu hoyilched sa, asaredched awa. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">tux虒史 c虒蓹d  tux虒史ub蓹d k史i sg史a蕯s sc虒蓹涩x虒蓹c虒蓹bs, tuhuyilc虒蓹d sa蕯, 蕯蓹s蕯蓹x虒idc虒蓹d 蕯蓹w始蓹.</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                              
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al sbosatlils ched tla rab dhual ku dsgwa dtskwadad, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al sbuusa涩ils c虒蓹d 涩ux虒aab dx史蕯al k史i dsg史a蕯 d胜蓹k始史adad, </rdg>    
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the fourth time I will cry because of my own sin. </rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                  
      
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">ched tla s'tewielh aku gwalh soshababdhu siayus s'tewielh. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL"> c虒蓹d 涩ust始iwi涩 蕯蓹 k史i g史蓹涩 s蕯us虒蓹babd蓹x史 syayus s't蓹wi蓹涩. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">I will pray with a prayer for the workings of pity.</rdg>   
        </app></l> 
        
                                                      
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al stselatsatlils ched tla tehech dhual di Sherk-Siam tsahu milalam aku tsoku. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al sc蓹laca涩ils c虒蓹d 涩utihic虒 dx史蕯al di蕯 s虒蓹q si蕯ab 蕯蓹ca蓹x史 bil始蕯alla蕯蓹b 蕯蓹 k史i c蓹k史.</rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the fifth time I will pray unto God for confession to be straight.</rdg> 
        </app></l> 
        
                                                          
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">4. Aschal kwi tla adsiayus aku tsoku dhual ku rarasmilalam?  </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">4. 蕯蓹sc虒al k史i 涩uadsyayus 蕯蓹 k史i c蓹k史 dx史蕯al k史i x虒ax虒a sbil始蕯alla蕯蓹b.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">4. How will you work correctly for your holy confession?</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                              
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Zihi kwi tlo dsrwelch chitebed aku leple; lakrahu ched tla p'tleltsob; </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">d岫籭x史 k史i 涩udsx虒蓹lc虒 c虒'铆tbid 蕯蓹 k史i  leple;  lakrahu_??? c虒蓹d 涩up虝蓹茮'ilc蓹b;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">First I go aside and approach the priest; ??? I feel it </rdg>
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                  
      <l n="16">
        <app>
           <rdg wit="#Bo">al slewhatlels ched tla gwagwadad aku astsut: o dgwe debad leple,</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al s涩ix史a涩ils c虒蓹d 涩ug史ag史adad 蕯蓹 k史i 蕯蓹scut:  蕯u d蓹g史i d蓹bad leple,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">on the third time I will speak by saying: o father priest,</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                                      
      <l n="17">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">oshabits tsa, yare kra ta dtskwadad. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯us虒蓹bic 蕯蓹ca, y蓹x虒i x虒a蕯 t蓹 dd岫簧檏始史adad. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#LG">Have pity on me, for great is my sin.</rdg>
          </app></l>
        
                                                                          
      <l n="18">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al sbosatlels ched tla 'tewielh aku gwalh rarasmilalam s'tewielh, dhual tih卯lh : </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al sbuusa涩ils c虒蓹d 涩ut'iwi涩 蕯蓹 k史i g史蓹涩 x虒ax虒a sbil始蕯alla蕯蓹b st'iwi涩, dx史蕯al ti蕯i涩 :</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the fourth time I will pray the prayer of confession, i.e.,</rdg>
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                              
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">"Kra tu dtskwadad ate disduhspet锚degwasseb, ate disduhsgwadgwad ate disduhsiayus eba te wheladisduhsiayus." </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL"> "x虒a蕯 t蓹 dd岫簧檏始史adad 蕯蓹 t蓹 dsd蓹x史sp蓹tidg史as蓹b, 蕯蓹 t蓹 dsd蓹x史sg史adg史ad 蕯蓹 t蓹 dsd蓹x史syayus 蕯ib蓹 t蓹 x史i蕯l蓹dsyayus."</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                  
      <l n="20">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al stselatsatlels ched tla haidhuthu ku leple aku des hagwahu whe tla milalam. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al c蓹laca涩ils c虒蓹d 涩uhaydx史tx史 k史i leple 蕯蓹 k史i dshag史蓹x史 x史i蕯 涩ubil始蕯alla蕯蓹b. </rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the fifth time I will make known to the priest how long I have not confessed (???).</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                      
      <l n="21">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al sielatsatlels ched tla haidhuthu ku leple aku tus hoyuds whe ku dtskwadad. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al sy蓹la蕯ca涩ils c虒蓹d 涩uhaydx史tx史 k史i l蓹pl蓹 蕯蓹 k史i tushuyuds x史i蕯 k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad. </rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the sixth time I will make known to the priest how I will eliminate my sin.</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                          
      <l n="22">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Al stsoksatlels ched tla haidhuthu ku leple aku tu dskrpaleku. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯al c虝u蕯k史sa涩ils c虒蓹d 涩uhaydx史tx史 k史i l蓹pl蓹 蕯蓹 k史i tudsq蓹palik史.</rdg>  
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the seventh time I will make known to the priest my folly.</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                              
      <l n="23">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo"> Al stkracheatlels ched tla haidhuthu leple aku tus balets ku dtskwadad, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL"> 蕯al stqac虒i蕯a涩ils c虒蓹d 涩uhaydx史tx史 l蓹pl蓹 蕯蓹 k史i tubalyic k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad, </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">On the eighth time I will make known to the priest the forgetting of my sin (??).</rdg>
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                  
      <l n="24">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">hoi ched tla reched ku tlewo't dtskwadad.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">huy c虒蓹d 涩ux虒蓹c虒蓹d k史i  涩u????? dd岫簧檏始史adad.</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                      
      <l n="25">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">5. Tla asared kwi tla adsrached ku adtskwadad dhual leple?</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">5. 涩u蕯蓹s蕯蓹x虒id k史i 涩(u)adss虒ac虒蓹d k史i add岫簧檏始史adad dx史蕯al leple.</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                          
      <l n="26">
         <app>
           <rdg wit="#Bo">Zihu kwi tlo dselid ku dtskwadad, ched tla reched, lakrahu ched tla haidhuthu ku leple dhual tih卯lh segwils ku dtskwadad, </rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#BL">d岫籭x史 k史i 涩uds蕯ilid k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad, c虒蓹d 涩ux虒蓹c虒蓹d, lakrahu_??? c虒蓹d 涩uhaydx史tx史 k史i leple dx史蕯al tih^i涩_ s蓹gwils_ k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad, </rdg>     
        </app></l>     
                                                                                                                  
      <l n="28">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">'tlalba asista dhual tih卯lh sbibadels ku dtskwadad. </rdg>   
          <rdg wit="#BL"> 'tlalba_ asista_ dx史蕯al ti蕯i涩 sbibad蓹ls_ k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad. </rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                      
      <l n="29">
         <app>
           <rdg wit="#Bo"> Whe kwi tlo desyetseb aku pa'tla'tl aku boku stab kra; </rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#BL">x史i蕯 k史i 涩udsy蓹c蓹b 蕯蓹 k史i p始a茮始a茮始 蕯蓹 k史i b蓹k始史 stab x虒a蕯; </rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#LG">I will not speak in vain of any thing ???</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                          
      <l n="30">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula whe kwi tlo desyetseb gwalh lale tskwadad.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">g史蓹l x史i蕯 k史i 涩udsy蓹c蓹b g史蓹涩 l蓹li蕯 d岫簧檏始史adad.</rdg>     
          <rdg wit="#LG">and I will not talk about others' sins.</rdg>
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                              
      <l n="31">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">6. Abil tlo hoyahu kwi tla adsrached ku adstskwadad, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">6. 蕯蓹bil始 涩uhuy蓹x史 k史i 涩(u)adsx虒蓹c虒蓹d k史i adsd岫簧檏始史adad, </rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                  
      <l n="32">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula aschal kwi tlo adsgwagwadad ? </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">g史蓹l 蕯蓹sc虒al k史i 涩(u)adsg史ag史adad?</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="33">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Abil tlo hoyahu ku tlo desrached ku dtskwadad, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">abil始 涩uhuy蓹x史 k史i 涩(u)dsx虒蓹c虒蓹d k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad, </rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="34">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">ched tla gwagwadad aku astsut: </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">c虒蓹d 涩(u)g史ag史adad 蕯蓹 k史i 蕯蓹scut :</rdg>    
          <rdg wit="#LG">I will speak by saying this:</rdg>
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                              
      <l n="35">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">dilh sbokrwels hahu ta aslarduhched dtskwadad, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">di涩 sb史ks虒w蓹ls_ hahu_ ta_ aslas虒duhc虒蓹d dsd岫簧檏始史史adad, </rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                  
      <l n="36">
                                                                                                                                                    
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">ched atleba whobed kwa aswhalhched saidhu dtskwadad ; </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">c虒蓹d atl蓹ba_ wh史b蓹d_ kwa_ aswha涩c虒蓹d saidhu_ dsd岫簧檏始史adad ; </rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="37">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">halh kwi gwa adsoshabits dgwe Sherk-Siam, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">ha蕯涩 k史i g史ads蕯us虒abic d蓹g史i s虒蓹q si蕯ab, </rdg>     
          <rdg wit="#LG">it would be good if you, God, were to pity me, </rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="38">
           <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">eba dgwe debad leple halh kwi gwa adsoshabits, </rdg> 
             <rdg wit="#BL">蕯ib蓹 d蓹g史i蕯 dbad leple ha蕯涩 k史i g史ads蕯us虒abic,</rdg> 
             <rdg wit="#LG">or if you, father priest, were to pity me, </rdg>  
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                              
      <l n="39">
         <app>
            <rdg wit="#Bo">chahu tla haidhutobsh, asared kwi tlo dskrpaleku; </rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#BL">c虒蓹x史 涩uhaydx史tubs虒,  蕯蓹s蕯蓹x虒id k史i 涩udsq蓹palik史;</rdg>     
         </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                  
      <l n="40">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">'tlob chahu ohoyud  whe ku dtskawdad, abil as astsut ku adrechbits. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">茮始ub c虒蓹x史 蕯uhuyud x史i蕯 k史i dd岫籯awdad, abil始 as_ astsut_ k史i adx虒蓹c虒bic.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#LG">it would be good if you were to make null my sin, ??????? </rdg> 
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="41">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Lakrahu ched tla orthu tih卯lh : "ate dsgwa askrop drech."  </rdg> 
            <rdg wit="#BL">lakra hu_ c虒蓹d tla_ 史s虒thu_ ti蕯i涩 茮始_ "at蓹_ dsg史a蕯 asks虒史p_ dx虒蓹c虒." </rdg>    
           </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="42">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Hoi chida tla astlabot aku tsoku, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">huy c虒蓹da tla_ astlab史t_ 蕯蓹 k史i cuk史,</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                              
      <l n="43">
          <app>
            <rdg wit="#Bo">tlo abietebad aku leple aku dsahukrpaleku, </rdg> 
            <rdg wit="#BL"> 涩u蕯abyit蓹bad 蕯蓹 k史i leple 蕯蓹 k史i ds蓹x史q蓹palik史, </rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                  
      <l n="44">
         <app>
             <rdg wit="#Bo">ched tla dgwad al ta drech ku gwalh leple tlus dhudgwets, </rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#BL">c虒蓹d 涩udg史ad 蕯al t蓹 dx虒蓹c虒 k史i g史蓹涩 leple 涩usdx史hud蓹g史ic, </rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="45">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">abie tlo hoyahu ku tlo dsdhudgwetob aku leple, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">abi蓹_ 涩uhuyah蓹x史 k史i 涩udsdhud蓹g史it蓹b 蕯蓹 k史i  l蓹pl蓹 ,</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="46">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">ched tla rabthu ti drech, ched tla elid ku gwalh soshababdhu siayus s'tewielh.  </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL"> c虒蓹d 涩ux虒aabtx史 ti dx虒蓹c虒, c虒蓹d 涩u蕯ilid k史i g史蓹涩 s蕯us虒蓹babdx史 syayus st始iwi涩.</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                              
      <l n="47">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Lakrahu ched tla welekr dhual leple, gwa ohoyud as whe ku dtskwadad.</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL"> _ laks虒ahu_ c虒蓹d 涩uwiliq始史 dx史蕯al leple, g史蓹蕯uhuyud蓹s x史i蕯 k史i dd岫簧檏始史adad.</rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                  
      <l n="48">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">7.  Abil leple tlo tsotbitsid ohoyahu chahu, chahu tlo aredahu?</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">7. 蕯蓹bil始 leple 涩ucut蓹bicid 蕯uhuy蓹x史 c虒蓹x史, c虒蓹x史 涩u蕯蓹x虒id蓹x史蕯</rdg>    
        </app></l> 
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="49">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">Abil leple tlo tsotbsh ohoyahu chahu, ched tla or,</rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">蕯蓹bil始 l蓹pl蓹 涩ucut蓹bs虒 蕯uhuy蓹x史 c虒蓹x史, c虒蓹d 涩u蕯ux虒史,</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="50">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">ched tla gwagwadad aku masi dhual ku Sherk-Siam, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">c虒蓹d 涩ug史ag史adad 蕯蓹 k史i masi dx史蕯al k史i s虒蓹q si蕯ab,</rdg>    
          <rdg wit="#BL">I will speak of mercy to God</rdg>  
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                              
      <l n="51">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">ched tla 'tehech dhual di Sherk-Siam, </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">c虒蓹d 涩utihic虒 dx史蕯al di蕯 s虒蓹q si蕯ab, </rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                                  
      <l n="52">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">tlhtsahu kwerkrwel, hoi ched tla hoyud tsoku ku tu dskrpalekutob aku leple. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">t涩 蕯蓹ca蓹x史 q史iq始史il, huy c虒蓹d 涩uhuyud c蓹k史 k史i tudsq蓹palik史tub 蕯蓹 k史i leple.</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                                      
      <l n="53">
         <app>
           <rdg wit="#Bo"> Aku tlo dspet锚degwasseb dhual di Sherk-Siam, </rdg> 
           <rdg wit="#BL">蕯蓹 k史i 涩udsp蓹tidg史as蓹b dx史蕯al di蕯 s虒蓹q si蕯ab,</rdg>     
        </app></l>
        
                                                                                                                                                                                                                          
      <l n="54">
         <app>
          <rdg wit="#Bo">gula whe la halh kwi gwa dsbahatsut. </rdg> 
          <rdg wit="#BL">g史蓹l x史i蕯 l蓹ha蕯涩 k史i g史蓹 dsbahatcut.</rdg>    
        </app></l> 

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>